for patients who get anxiety when
starting trt does the wired feeling or
anxiety fade after a few months okay I
like this question
so it's going to massively depend on the
individual but does it fade yes does it
fade down to nothing it depends on if
the individual has underlying issues
with anxiety so testosterone is not a
stimulant per se it doesn't fall into
the category that would identify it as a
stimulant but it stimulates the central
nervous system system especially when
someone is naive to the dosing so when
the body gets an acute spike in
testosterone whether they're initiating
trt or when you know guys are doing
cycles of anabolics for example it it
causes more activation of the central
nervous system the problem is that if
someone is predisposed to anxiety what
feels like activation will then lead to
an anxiety response um I use the analogy
that and it's it's a you know in the
sport boxing it doesn't make any sense
why these two people would be fighting
but if you took two boxers one who'd won
every fight and one who'd lost every
fight and they went into the boxing ring
together as they're walking out and the
music's playing they're both going to
have the same physiological sensations
of anticipation which is butterflies in
the stomach shortness of breath elevated
heart rate you know all of that stuff
that's very normal but the guy who's won
every fight will associate that with
Victory and excitement and you know
positive anticipation whereas the guy
who's lost every fight will associate
that with failure pain losing
embarrassment humiliation but
physiologically they're the same so if
someone is predisposed towards anxious
thinking and has an anxious thought
process then this is definitely going to
be something that is going to
potentially be uncomfortable for that
first few months of treatment so the
things that I find that are very helpful
for that period CBD oil works very well
we often recommend it for my clinic in
Australia uh magnesium works well phidal
serine works well I've done lectures on
all these supplements on the channel um
those ones work really well as well as
if people are drinking uh coffee or
caffeine combining it with theanine can
help to take the edge off but this can
also potentially if it doesn't fade and
resolve be an indicator that the dose is
too high so it is very important that
the individual gets that blood test at
about 8 to 12 weeks when the provider
orders the first blood test I would hope
which is when levels reach a stable
concent to make sure that the dose is
correct and sometimes guys who are more
prone to anxiety because sometimes
testosterone helps with anxiety
sometimes it makes it worse and it
depends on you know where it's all
coming from but sometimes guys who are
feeling like cranked and like wired like
you know jacked up in a bad way
sometimes they do better starting with
the dose a little bit lower and then
tight trading it up very gradually every
3 to four months rather than shooting
straight for a higher level because
their nervous system and their
psychology needs time to adjust so yes
it does back off once your body gets
used to it assuming the dose is correct
but a baseline anxiety state can be
exacerbated by higher antigen levels and
that's why it's also important that the
root cause of the anxiety is addressed I
like things like mindfulness meditation
martial arts stretching and Mobility um
all of these things really help as well
as looking at um you know different
forms of cognitive behavioral therapy
you know how we think and how we look at
things and sometimes it actually helps
for guys to speak to a therapist which I
know gets a bad rap but sometimes it is
helpful so it's important to look at it
holistically
[Music]